Guide to the McLoughlin Brothers, Inc. Woodblocks Circa 1840-1920 PC 001
New-York Historical Society
- Series IX. Alphabet books
  - Young America series: A Apple Pie (Offsite-box 22, Box 3F (7))
    12 woodblocks printed using chromoxylography including title page.
  - Depictions of Victorian initials (Offsite-box 25, Box 3F (8))
    14 woodblocks.
    Incomplete uppercase alphabet in which letters are illustrated with characters from nursery rhymes and fairytales.
  - Characters in alphabet rhyme (Offsite-box 23, Box 3F (9))
    Blocks depict original characters used in an alphabet rhyme; no letters are represented.
- Series X. Conserved woodblocks
  - Conserved woodblocks (Offsite-box 31, Box 5E (1))
    14 woodblocks including 1 frame and a woodblock from Dog's Grand Dinner Party engraved by Edward P. Cogger. The title is found in the Library's rare children's book collection under the call number YC1869 .Dog.
    These woodblocks were conserved and rehoused in 2018 in consideration of a treatment and rehousing plan.
  - Mother Goose in New York exhibition box (Offsite-box 32, Box 5F (1))
    Picture Alphabet, title page (YC1865 .Pic); Lord Bateman, 1 woodblock (YC1838 .Fairy); The Death and Burial of Pretty Cock Robin, 1 woodblock (YC1838 .Fairy); Miss Vanity's Holiday: The Passionate Child, 4 woodblocks (YC-f 18-- .Mis); Little ABC Book, 2 woodblocks (YC1884 .Little ABC); Happy Changes, 1 woodblock (YC1844 .P); Funny Alphabet, 4 woodblocks (YC1838 .Fairy); Grandma Stories, 2 woodblocks (YC1838 .Fairy); Lazy Charlotte, title page (YC1870.Laz); Jemmy String, 1 woodblock (YC1870 .Jem); Sammy Tickletooth, 1 woodblock (YC1870 .Sam); Little Goody Two Shoes – Spelling Game, multiple-bolted title page (24 woodblocks); [Alphabet], multiple bolted (21 woodblocks); Cruel Frederick, Story of, title page; Little Suck-a-Thumb, title page; 33 woodblocks; Truant Peter, title page; Johnny Sliderlegs, title page; Passionate Child, title lettering; 17 woodblocks; 2 multiple-bolted woodblocks (8 each).
    These woodblocks were conserved and rehoused for the 1992 New-York Historical Society exhibition, Mother Goose in New York: McLoughlin Books and the Art of Woodcut Illustration.
- Series XI. Damaged woodblocks
  The woodblocks in this collection have suffered through a fire and a flood before being donated to the Patricia D. Klingenstein Library in 1989. While many of the woodblocks are slightly damaged, the woodblocks in this series are damaged beyond recognition and/or research use.
  - Charred woodblocks (Offsite-box 23, Box 3E (1))
    80+ charred woodblocks.
  - Work box (Offsite-box 24, Box 3E (2))
  - Children in the Wood (Offsite-box 25, Box 4A (1))
    6 woodblocks including fragments with doweled joints.
  - Early woodblocks by Robert H. Elton (Offsite-box 24, Box 4A (2))
    2 woodblocks; burnt fragments.
  - Sarah J. Hale series (Offsite-box 24, Box 4A (3))
    13 burnt fragments including title pages for The Good-Natured Little Girl and The Dilatory Little Boy.
  - Chromoxylographic woodblocks (Offsite-box 24, Box 4A (4))
    8 fire-damaged woodblocks.
  - Apple Pie title page (Offsite-box 24, Box 4A (5))
    1 fire-damaged chromoxylographic woodblock.
  - Miscellaneous doweled joint fragments (Offsite-box 26, Box 4B (1))
    8 woodblocks in fragments.
  - Miscellaneous bolted fragments (Offsite-box 27, Box 4B (2))
    11 charred woodblocks in fragments.
  - Mother Goose woodblocks (Offsite-box 26, Box 4B (3))
    8 charred woodblocks.
  - Idle Boy (Offsite-box 26, Box 4B (4))
    4 damaged woodblocks.
  - Fragments of furniture depictions (Offsite-box 29, Box 4C (1))
    8 woodblocks including McLoughlin piano.
  - Depictions of children with books (Offsite-box 27, Box 4C (2))
    2 charred woodblocks.
  - Mother Goose's Rhymes title page (Offsite-box 25, Box 4C (3))
    1 broken multiple woodblock.
  - Sploit Piggy Wiggy engraved by Edward P. Cogger (Offsite-box 29, Box 4C (4))
    1 fragmented multiple block.
  - Dame Wonder series (Offsite-box 27, Box 4C (5))
    2 fragmented woodblocks.
  - Miscellaneous fragments (1 of 2) (Offsite-box 27, Box 4C (6), 4C (9), 4C (10))
    20+ fragments of woodblocks.
  - Miscellaneous fragments (2 of 2) (Offsite-box 29, Box 4C (7), 4C (8))
  - Miscellaneous charred woodblocks (Offsite-box 27, Box 4C (11))
    3 charred woodblocks.
  - Fragments title pages (Offsite-box 30, Box 4C (12))
    9 woodblocks including an unknown Sarah J. Hale series title; The Practical Letter Writer; Who Would A'Wooing Go?; Aladdin or the Wonderful Lamp; Paper Furniture; and The Child's Cotton Plant.
  - Goody Two Shoes Story Book title page (Offsite-box 28, Box 4D (1))
    4 broken woodblocks.
  - Dame Wonder series (Offsite-box 29, Box 4D (2))
    11 charred woodblocks and fragments.
  - Fat Boy (Offsite-box 28, Box 4D (3))
  - Miscellaneous multiple doweled fragments engraved by Edward P. Cogger (Offsite-box 29, Box 4D (4))
    10 fragments of woodblocks.
  - Animal scales (Offsite-box 30, Box 4E (1))
  - King Donkey engraved by Edward P. Cogger (Offsite-box 30, Box 4E (2))
    1 fragmented woodblock.
  - More miscellaneous charred woodblocks (1 of 2) (Offsite-box 30, Box 4E (3))
    20+ woodblocks.
  - More miscellaneous charred woodblocks (2 of 2) (Offsite-box 28, Box 4E (4))